QIYU WU

Email: wuqiyu576@gmail.com · Personal Website: qiyuw.github.io · LinkedIn: qiyuw

Keywords: NLP; Text Embeddings; LLMs/VLMs.

SUMMARY

Ph.D. specializing in NLP, focusing on learning text embeddings/representation [C8, C7, C5, C4, J1, C3] and fine-grained LLMs/VLMs [C12, M1, C11]. I also collaborate on entity representation [C6] and reinforcement learning [C10] for expanding my scope. These works have been presented at conferences such as ACL, EMNLP, ICLR, NAACL, ICML, etc.

EDUCATION

- The University of Tokyo, Ph.D. Degree in Information Science & Technology.	2021.10 - 2024.09
Ph.D. at Tsuruoka Lab; JSPS DC2 Fellowship; JST SPRING Fellowship.	
- Peking University, M.Sc. Degree in Computer Software & Theory.	2018.09 - 2021.07
- Sichuan University, B.Eng. Degree in Computer Science & Technology.	2014.09 - 2018.07
RESEARCH EXPERIENCES	
- Ph.D. at UTokyo, Tsuruoka Lab	2021.10 - 2024.09
Word-level preference for LLM-based machine translation [C12]; Scene graph alignment for texture and the second se	xt-to-image evaluation [C11];
Word alignment pre-training [C5]; Cross-lingual text embeddings [C8, C7].	
- Research Intern at Sony, Creative AI Lab	2023.06 - 2023.09
Bi-modal data augmentation for mitigating reporting bias in visual-language dataset [M1].	
- Visiting Student at UC San Diego	2023.01 - 2023.02
Generalized diffusion model [C9].	
- Research Intern at Microsoft	2021.10 - 2022.02
Multiple positive examples in sentence embeddings with contrastive learning [C4].	
- Research Intern at Microsoft Research, Asia	2020.04 - 2021.06
Acceleration of language pre-training via better rare word representation [C3].	
- R&D Intern at Baidu Research	2019.10 - 2020.02

RESEARCH PAPERS

* indicates equal contribution; † indicates students mentored by me.

Multi-task transportation prediction [C2]; Route mode recommendation in Baidu Maps.

- [C12] Qiyu Wu, Masaaki Nagata, Zhongtao Miao, Yoshimasa Tsuruoka. "Word Alignment as Preference for Machine Translation", (EMNLP 2024, main conference long paper, Oral).
- [C11] Qiyu Wu, Zilong Wu, Yoshimasa Tsuruoka. "SGA: Scene Graph Alignment for Evaluation of Text-to-Image Generation", (KDD 2024 Workshop HI-AI).
- [C10] Yuting Tang, Xin-Qiang Cai, Yao-Xiang Ding, Qiyu Wu, Guoqing Liu, Masashi Sugiyama. "Reinforcement Learning from Bagged Reward", (ICML 2024 Workshop ARLET).
- [C9] Guangyi Liu, Yu Wang, Zeyu Feng, Qiyu Wu, Liping Tang, Yuan Gao, Zhen Li, Shuguang Cui, Julian McAuley, Eric P. Xing, Zichao Yang, Zhiting Hu. "Unified Generation, Reconstruction, and Representation: Generalized Diffusion with Adaptive Latent Encoding-Decoding", in the Forty-first International Conference on Machine Learning. (ICML 2024).
- [C8] Zhongtao Miao[†], Qiyu Wu, Kaiyan Zhao, Zilong Wu, Yoshimasa Tsuruoka. "Enhancing Cross-lingual Sentence Embedding for Low-resource Languages with Word Alignment", in the 2022 Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (NAACL 2024, findings).
- [C7] Kaiyan Zhao^{†*}, Qiyu Wu^{*}, Xin-Qiang Cai, Yoshimasa Tsuruoka. "Leveraging Multi-lingual Positive Instances in Contrastive Learning to Improve Sentence Embedding", in *the 18th Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics* (EACL 2024, main conference long paper).

- [C6] Shiwen Wu, Qiyu Wu, Honghua Dong, Wen Hua, Xiaofang Zhou. "Blocker and Matcher Can Mutually Benefit: A Co-Learning Framework for Low-Resource Entity Resolution.", *Proc. VLDB Endow.* (2024). Will appear at Very Large Databases Conf. (VLDB 2024, research track paper).
- [M1] Qiyu Wu, Mengjie Zhao, Yutong He, Lang Huang, Junya Ono, Hiromi Wakaki, Yuki Mitsufuji. "Towards Reporting Bias in Visual-language Datasets: Bi-modal Data Augmentation by Decoupling Object-attribute Association", *preprint* (arXiv:2310.01330).
- [C5] Qiyu Wu, Masaaki Nagata, Yoshimasa Tsuruoka. "WSPAlign: Word Alignment Pre-training via Large-Scale Weakly Supervised Span Prediction", in the 61st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL 2023, main conference long paper).
- [C4] Qiyu Wu, Chongyang Tao, Tao Shen, Can Xu, Xiubo Geng, Daxin Jiang. "PCL: Peer-Contrastive Learning with Diverse Augmentations for Sentence Embeddings", in *Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP 2022, main conference long paper)*.
- [J1] Yutao Xie[†], Qiyu Wu, Wei Chen and Tengjiao Wang. "Stable Contrastive Learning for Self-Supervised Sentence Embeddings With Pseudo-Siamese Mutual Learning", in *IEEE/ACM Transactions on Audio, Speech, and Language Processing* (*TASLP*), vol. 30, pp. 3046-3059, 2022.
- [C3] Qiyu Wu*, Chen Xing*, Yatao Li, Guolin Ke, Di He, Tie-Yan Liu. "Taking Notes on the Fly Helps Language Pre-Training", in the Ninth International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR 2021).
- [C2] Hao Liu*, Qiyu Wu*, Fuzhen Zhuang, Xinjiang Lu, Dejing Dou, Hui Xiong. "Community-Aware Multi-Task Transportation Demand Prediction", in *Thirty-Fifth AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI 2021)*.
- [C1] Dechuan Yang*, Qiyu Wu*, Wei Chen, Tengjiao Wang, Zhen Qiu, Di Liu. "Stance Detection with Stance-wise Convolution Network", in the 2022 CCF International Conference on Natural Language Processing and Chinese Computing.

[J]: Journal paper; [C]: Conference paper; [M]: Manuscript; [N]: Non-refereed.

MENTORING AND SERVICES

• Mentoring:	
- Zhongtao Miao, Ph.D. student at The University of Tokyo, published [C8, C12].	2023 - 2024
- Kaiyan Zhao, Ph.D. student at The University of Tokyo, published [C7].	2022 - 2024
 Yutao Xie, Ph.D. student at Peking University, published [J1]. 	2020 - 2021
• Teaching Assistant of "Social Implications of Computing" at Peking University.	2019 Summer
• Reviewer of ACL Rolling Review, EMNLP, ICLR, NeurIPS, ICML, etc.	2021 – Present